So now that we understand what a secure
PRG is, and we understand what semantic
现在我们知道了什么是安全PRG，什么是语义安全
security means, we can actually argue that
a stream cipher with a secure PRG is, in
因此我们可以证明具有安全PRG的流密码是语义安全的
fact, a semantically secure. So that's our
goal for this, segment. It's a fairly
这就是我们本节的目标
straightforward proof, and we'll see how
it goes. So the theory we wanna prove is
这是个相当简单的证明，我们来看是如何做的
that, basically, given a generator G that
happens to be a secured, psedo-random
我们要证明的理论是，给定一个安全的伪随机数发生器G
generator. In fact, the stream cipher
that's derived from this generator is
由此发生器推出的流密码将是语义安全的
going to be semantically secure. Okay and
I want to emphasize. That there was no
然而，我需要强调
hope of proving a theorem like this for
perfect secrecy. For Shannons concept of
基于香农定理本身的完善保密性，想对类似的理论进行证明是不可能的
perfect secrecy. Because we know that a
stream cipher can not be perfectly
因为我们知道流密码的密钥太短，不满足完善保密性
secure because it has short keys. And
perfect secrecy requires the keys to be as
完善保密性要求密钥至少要和明文一样长
long as the message. So this is really
kind of the first example the we see where
那么这是我们看到的
we're able to prove that a cipher with
short keys has security. The concept of
第一个真正能够证明短密钥密码也具有安全性的例子
security is semantic security. And this
actually validates that, really, this is a
即语义安全的概念
very useful concept. And in fact, you
know, we'll be using semantic security
这也说明语义安全是一个很重要的概念
many, many times throughout the course.
Okay, so how do we prove a theory like
这门课我们将会反复用到语义安全这个概念
this? What we're actually gonna be doing,
is we're gonna be proving the
那么我们如何证明这个定理？事实上我们将证明它的逆否命题
contrapositive. What we're gonna show is
the following. So we're gonna prove this
我们来进行如下证明
statement down here, but let me parse it
for you. Suppose. You give me a semantic
我们要证的这个命题，让我来解析一下
security adversary A. What we'll do is
we'll build PRG adversary B to satisfy
假设有一个威胁语义安全的敌手A，我们要构造一个PRG敌手B来满足这个不等式
this inequality here. Now why is this
inequality useful? Basically what do we
为什么要满足这个不等式？我们知道什么？
know? We know that if B is an efficient
adversary. Then we know that since G is a
我们知道如果B是一个有效敌手，那么由于发生器G是安全的
secure generator, we know that this
advantage is negligible, right? A secure
我们就知道这个优势是可以被忽略的，对吧？
generator has a negligible advantage
against any efficient statistical test. So
一个安全的发生器对于一切有效统计测试都具有可忽略的优势
the right hand side, basically, is gonna
be negligible. But because the right hand
所以右边基本上是可以忽略的
side is negligible, we can deduce that the
left hand side is negligible.
由于右边是可忽略的，我们可以推断左边也是可忽略的
And therefore, the adversary that you looked
at actually has negligible advantage in
因此敌手对于流密码E的优势是可忽略的
attacking the stream cipher E. Okay. So
this is how this, this will work.
这就是这个式子的含义
Basically all we have to do is given an
adversary A we're going to build an
给定任一敌手A，我们要构造出一个敌手B。
adversary B. We know that B has negligible
advantage against generator but that
我们知道B对于发生器的优势是可忽略的
implies that A has negligible advantage
against the stream cipher.
这意味着A对于流密码的优势也是可忽略的
So let's do that. So all we have to do again
is given A, we have to build B.
这就是我们要做的，给定A，我们只需要构造B
So let A be a semantic security adversary against
the stream cipher. So let me remind you
设A为一流密码下的语义安全的敌手
what that means. Basically, there's a
challenger. The challenger starts off by
回想一下这里的含义。即有一个挑战者选择密钥K
choosing the key K. And then the adversary
is gonna output two messages, two equal
然后敌手输出两个等长的明文M0和M1
length messages. And he's gonna receive
the encryption of M0 or M1
然后他将会收到M0或者M1的密文，并输出B1
and outputs B1. Okay, that's
what a semantic security adversary is
这就是语义安全的敌手所做的
going to do. So now we're going to start
playing games with this adversary. And
现在我们与这个敌手来玩这个游戏
that's how we're going to prove our lemma. Alright, so the first thing
我们就是这样来证明引理的
we're going to do is we're going to make
the challenger. Also choose a random R.
首先我们要构造挑战者，并让其选择一个随机字符串R
Okay, a random string R. So, well you know
the adversary doesn't really care what the
敌手不关心挑战者内部是如何实现的
challenger does internally. The challenger
never uses R, so this doesn't affect the
挑战者从来不使用R
adversary's advantage at all. The
adversary just doesn't care that the
所以这不影响敌手的优势，敌手也不关心挑战者挑选的R
challenger also picks R. But now comes the
trick. What we're going to do is we're
然而这里有一个技巧
going to, instead of encrypting using GK.
We're going to encrypt using R. You can
我们使用R来加密而不是G(K)
see basically what we're doing
here. Essentially we're changing the
你能看到这里我们是怎么做的
challenger so now the challenge
cipher text is encrypted using a
我们使挑战者输出的密文使用真随机数进行加密
truly random pad. As opposed to just pseudo
random pad GK. Okay. Now, the property of
而不是使用伪随机数G(k)
the pseudo-random generator is that its
output is indistinguishable from truly
这个伪随机数发生器的性质是，它的输出与真随机是不可区分的
random. So, because the PRG is secure, the
adversary can't tell that we made this
因为这个PRG是安全的，敌手无法发现其中的变化
change. The adversary can't tell that we
switched from a pseudo-random string to a
敌手不知道我们是否从伪随机字符串换成了真随机字符串
truly random string. Again, because the generator is secure. Well, but now look at
这又是因为这个发生器是安全的
the game that we ended up with. So the
adversary's advantage couldn't have
现在我们来看这个游戏
changed by much, because he can't tell the
difference. But now look at the game that
敌手的优势没有明显变化，因为他无法发现其中的区别
we ended up with. Now this game is truly a
one time pad game. This a semantic
现在这个游戏是一个一次一密的游戏
security game against the one time pad.
Because now the adversary is getting a one
是一次一密下的语义安全
time pad encryption of M0 or M1 But in the
one time pad we know that the adversaries
因为敌手得到的M0和M1的密文使用了一次一密
advantage is zero, because you can't beat
the one time pad. The one time pad is
我们知道一次一密下敌手的优势为0，因为一次一密是不可破的
secure Unconditionally secure. And as a
result, because of this. Essentially
一次一密是无条件安全的
because the adversary couldn't have told
the difference when
因此当我们从伪随机变为真随机时，敌手无法发现这里的区别
we moved from pseudo random to random. But he couldn't win the
random game. That also means that he
他不能赢下真随机的游戏
couldn't win the sudo random game. And as
a result, the stream cipher, the original
也表示他不能赢下这个伪随机的游戏，因此最初的流密码一定是安全的
stream cipher must be secure. So that's
the intuition for how the proof is gonna go.
这就是证明的直观思路
But I wanna do it rigorously once.
From now on, we're just gonna argue by
然而我想再来严格地证明一下
playing games with our challenger. And, we
won't be doing things as formal as I'm
从现在开始，我们与挑战者进行游戏
gonna do next. But I wanna do formally and
precisely once, just so that you see how
以后我们不会这样正式来做，但这一次我想正式而精确地说明证明的原理
these proofs actually work. Okay, so I'm
gonna have to introduce some notation. And
我们需要引入一些记号
I'll do the usual notation, basically. If
the original semantics are here at the
基本都用常见的记号
beginning, when we're actually using a
pseudo-random pad, I'm gonna use W0 and W1
使用伪随机时，我用W0和W1分别表示
to denote the event that the adversary
outputs one, when it gets the encryption
敌手在接收到M0或M1的密文的情况下
of M0, or gets the encryption of M1,
respectively. Okay? So W0 corresponds to
输出1的事件
outputting 1 when receiving the
encryption of M0. And W1 corresponds
所以W0表示接收到M0的密文时输出1
to outputting 1 when receiving the encryption of M1. So that's the standard
W1表示接收到M1的密文时输出1
definition of semantic security. Now once
we flip to the random pad. I'm gonna use
这是语义安全的标准定义。现在来看真随机
R0 and R1 to denote the event that the
adversary outputs 1 when receiving the
我用R0和R1分别表示敌手在接收到M0和M1的密文的情况下
one-type pad encryption of M0 or the
one-time pad encryption of M1. So we have
输出1的事件
four events, W0, W1 from the original
semmantics security game, and R0 and R1
所以我们得到4个事件。W0，W1来自最初语义安全的游戏
from the semmantics security game once we
switch over to the one-time pad. So now
R0，R1来自切换到一次一密后的游戏
let's look at relations between these
variables. So first of all, R0 and R1 are
现在我们来看这些变量的关系
basically events from a semmantics
security game against a one-time pad. So
首先，R0和R1是一次一密下语义安全的事件
the difference between these probabilities
is that, as we said, basically the
因此概率之差就等于
advantage of algorithm A, of adversary A,
against the one-time pad. Which we know is
敌手A对于一次一密的优势，即为0
zero. Okay, so that's great. So that
basically means that probability of, of R0
很好，这表示R0的概率等于R1的概率
is equal to the probability of R1. So now,
let's put these events on a line, on a
我们来把这些事件放在一条线上
line segment between zero and one. So here
are the events. W0 and W1 are the events
区间在0到1之间
we're interested in. We wanna show that
these two are close. Okay. And the way
我们关心的是W0和W1，我们想证明它们很接近
we're going to do it is basically by
showing, oh and I should say, here is
我们要做的是
probability R0 and R1, it says
they're both same, I just put them in the
这里是R0和R1，它们相等，所以放在了一起
same place. What we're gonna do is we're
gonna show that both W0 and W1 are
我们要说明W0和W1都接近于Rb
actually close to the probability of RB
and as a result they must be close to one
所以它们彼此之间一定也接近
another. Okay, so the way we do that is
using a second claim, so now we're
我们利用第二个论断来说明
interested in the distance between
probability of Wb and the probability of
这里我们关注的是Wb和Rb之间的距离
Rb. Okay so we'll prove the claim in a
second. Let me just state the claim. The
我们稍后来证明这个论断，首先我来说明一下
claim says that there exists in adversary
B. Such that the difference of these two
这个论断指出存在敌手B
probabilities is basically the advantage
of B against the generator G and this is
使得这两个概率之差等于敌手B对于发生器G的优势，对b的两个取值都成立
for both b's. Okay? So given these two
claims, like the theorem is done because
因此给定了这两个论断，就证明了这个定理
basically what do we know. We know this
distance is less than the advantage of B
因为我们知道这个距离小于B对于G的优势
against G. That's from claim two and
similarly, this distance actually is even
根据论断2，这个距离就等于B对于G的优势
equal to, I'm not gonna say
less but is equal to the advantage. Of B
而不是小于B对于G的优势
against G, and as a result you can see
that the distance between W0 and W1
因此正如你所看到的
is basically almost twice the
advantage of B against G. That's basically
W0和W1之间的距离最多为B对于G优势的两倍
the thing that we are trying to prove.
Okay the only thing that remains is just
这就是我们要证明的
proving this claim two and if you think
about what claim two says, it basically
因此剩下要做的就是证明论断2
captures the question of what happens in
experiment zero what happens when we
论断2表示的是当伪随机G(k)被替换成真随机R后
replace the pseudo random pad GK, by
truly random pad R. Here in
实验0产生的变化
experiment zero say we're using the pseudo
random pad and here in experiment zero we
在这个实验0中，我们使用伪随机
are using a Truly random pad and we are
asking can the adversary tell the
而在这个实验0中则使用真随机
difference between these two and we wanna
argue that he cannot because the generator
我们让敌手分辨这两者，然后我们想证明这是不可能的，因为发生器是安全的
is secure. Okay so here's what we are
gonna do. So let's prove claim two. So we
这就是我们要做的，我们来证明论断2
are gonna argue that in fact there is a
PRG adversary B that has exactly the
我们要证明有一敌手B对于PRG的优势
difference of the two probabilities as
it's advantage. Okay and since the point
严格等于这两个概率之差
is since this is negligible this is
negligible. And that's basically what we
因为这个是可忽略的，这个也是可忽略的 这就是我们想证明的
wanted to prove. Okay, so let's look at
the statistical test b. So, what, our
我们来看统计测试b
statistical test b is gonna use adversary
A in his belly, so we get to build
我们的统计测试b将在内部用到敌手A
statistical test b however we want. As we
said, it's gonna use adversary A inside of
因此我们根据需要构建统计测试b 正如我们说过的，内部使用敌手A
it, for its operation, and it's a regular
statistical test, so it takes an n-bit
是一个常规的统计测试
string as inputs, and it's supposed to
output, you know, random or non-random,
使用n位比特字符串作为输入，判断输出随机或不随机，0还是1
zero or one. Okay, so let's see. So it's,
first thing it's gonna do, is it's gonna
我们来看它首先做了什么
run adversary A, and adversary A is gonna
output two messages, M0 and M1. And then,
运行敌手A，敌手A输出两个信息M0和M1
what adversary b's gonna do, is basically
gonna respond. With M0 XOR or the string that
敌手B用M0与输入的字符串异或，返回给A
it was given as inputs. Alright? That's
the statistical lesson, then. Whenever A
这就是这个统计测试
outputs, it's gonna output, its output.
And now let's look at its advantage. So
A的输出就是统计测试的输出 现在我们来看它的优势
what can we say about the advantage of
this statistical test against the
所以统计测试对于发生器的优势是多少？
generator? Well, so by definition, it's
the probability that, if you choose a
根据定义，如果你选择一个真随机字符串
truly random string. So here are 01 to the N, so probability
这里是^n
that R, that B outputs 1 minus the
probability, is that when we choose a
B输出1的概率减去当我们选择伪随机字符串时
pseudo random string, B outputs 1, okay?
Okay, but let's think about what this is.
B输出1的概率，对吧?
What can you tell me about the first
expressions? What can you tell me about
想一想第一个式子说明了什么？这个式子说明了什么？
this expression over here? Well, by the
definition that's exactly if you think
根据定义，想想这里发生的
about what's going on here, that's this is
exactly the probability R0 right?
这个式子就等于R0的概率，对吧？
Because this game that we are playing with
the adversary here is basically he helped
因为我们与敌手玩的这个游戏中敌手输出M0和M1
us M0 and M1 right here he helped add M0 and m1 and he got the encryption
他得到了M0和M1一次一密加密后的密文
of M0 under truly one time pad. Okay,
so this is basically a [inaudible]. Here
这就是一个概率
let me write this a little better. That's
the basic level probability of R0.
我来写的好看一点，这就是R0的概率
Now, what can we say about the next
expression, well what can we say about
那么第二个式子说明什么？
when B is given a pseudo random
string Y as input.
当B以伪随机字符串为输入时
Well in that case, this is exactly experiment zero and
true stream cipher game
这种情况下，这是实验0和真正的流密码的游戏
because now we're computing M XOR M0, XOR GK. This is
exactly W0.
现在我们计算M异或M0，异或G(k)，这就是W0
Okay, that's exactly what we have to prove. So it's kind of a trivial proof.
这正是我们要证明的，这是个很简单的证明
Okay, so that completes the proof of claim two. And again, just to
make sure this is all clear, once we have
好，论断2就证明完毕了 为确保讲清楚了
claim two, we know that W0 must be close
to W1, and that's the theorem.
一但证明了论断2，我们就知道W0一定接近于W1
That's what we have to prove. Okay, so now we've
established that a stream cypher is in
这就是我们要证明的定理 好的，现在我们证明了只要PRG是安全的
fact symmantically secure, assuming that
the PRG is secure.
流密码就是语义安全的